Edwin Augustus Porcher Collection
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
Comprises watercolor drawings from E.A. Porcher and R. Murdoch Smith's archaeological expedition to Cyrene (Libya) in 1860-1, some of which became the basis for engravings and lithographs in the publication History of the Recent Discoveries at Cyrene made during an Expedition to the Cyrenaica in 1860-1 (London, 1864). Extant are 89 drawings on Whatman paper in three sizes (58 views and 31 plans). 16 of these were donated by Porcher to the British museum in 1865 (5 watercolor views, 9 plans, 1 elevation, and 1 drawing of an inscription). The remaining 73 drawings (52 watercolor views, 20 plans, and 1 elevation) have been assigned new registration numbers by museum staff (2012,5033.1-73) (Celeste Farge, British Museum, Email Correspondence, May 20, 2013). A portion of these were donated to the Museum in 1894 by Cecil Du Pre Penton Powney (Porcher's nephew) and include Porcher's duplicates of drawings (with signature). A list on blue foolscap accompanying the watercolors identifies a total of 112 drawings, including a small sketchbook of 29 drawings from the Cyrene expedition. By all indications, the sketchbook was broken up and the drawings were individually mounted after it was obtained by the British Museum. Based on current holdings, some of the 112 watercolors are presumed lost (see Thorn 224). Unpublished illustrations fall under a numbering system (Porcher's system) as 87-137. The YCBA watercolors include a set numbered 70-86, possibly contiguous with the British Museum's watercolors.
The British Museum Central Archives has holdings including Smith and Porcher's letters from Cyrene to Charles Newton (Keeper, British Museum).
National Archives, Kew
Call number: MFQ 1/616
Comprises two portfolios of material related to Nathan Davis' excavations at Carthage. Includes Porcher's drawings, maps and plans: 'Plan of the peninsula of Carthage exhibiting the present excavations...': also showing Roman ruins above ground; large mosaic excavated at Carthage (now in British Museum); map of the peninsula of Carthage, showing the sites of excavations, ruins, the Lake of Tunis, roads, and terrain. All items were originally enclosed in despatches from Nathan Davis, 1857-1859.
British Columbia Archives, Victoria
Call numbers: PDP02857- PDP02884; C-05526; D-09121
Two views of Metlakatla (one a copy of a view in private collection) and an album containing 27 watercolors inscribed in ink and dated 1862-9. Duplication of subjects and compositions in the sketchbook indicates that some of these were preparatory versions for later works (now housed at the Beinecke Library). In 1863-4, Porcher produced images of the English south coast and Brazil (including Rio de Janeiro). He travelled through the Straits of Magellan and northwards up the coast of South America. After reaching Honolulu, Porcher sailed on to Esquimalt, Vancouver Island. Some of the 1866 views from these travels were engraved for the tenth and eleventh Annual Report of the Columbia Mission (1868 and 1869), which also gives an account of Porcher's visit north to the Tsimshian village and mission at Metlakatla. The collection was acquired in 1973.
Beinecke Library, New Haven
Call number: WA MSS S-1972
Comprises 53 watercolors dated April 1865 – September 1868, depicting subjects from Porcher's tour of duty to Esquimalt, the Royal Naval base on Vancouver Island, British Columbia aboard the HMS Sparrowhawk. Also includes: a journal, 240 pages, 8vo.; logbook 47 pages, 8vo.; and four documents commending Porcher's conduct, one of which promotes him to the standing of Captain, RN. The collection was acquired in 1972.
The Royal Navy was deployed in the Pacific to protect Britain's commercial and political interests in the Pacific, while also serving as diplomatic agents when necessary. A Crown colony of Vancouver Island was established to prevent American advancement into disputed territory and Esquimalt became the strategic base for British in the North Pacific. Porcher was made a magistrate so that he could arbitrate in disputes between tribal groups and the European populace (see E.A. Porcher journal, Beinecke Library). His interest in Northwest Coast cultural expressions is evident in his watercolors, where he documents Haida, Tsimshian and Coast Salish totem poles and house posts.
Danforth Art Museum, Framingham
Consists of 57 watercolors gifted in 1976 and 1977 by Robert Pirie. Exhibited as "The Grand Tour, Watercolors by E.A. Porcher" at the Danforth Art Museum in 1977. These drawings date to Porcher's later years, after his retirement from the Royal Navy (1872). The images represent sites encountered during travels to European spa and resort towns, cultural monuments, fortifications, and beauty spots such as Lake Como, Drachenfels mountain (on the Rhine), and Isola Bella. The recorded sights in Germany, Belgium, Bohemia, Austria and Italy reveal Porcher's abiding interest in local history. He takes great interest, for instance, in the Wurtemberg fortifications at Ulm, Castle of Godesberg Bacharach, San Vitale at Ravenna, Church of Santa Maria Assunta, Ehrenbreitstein Fortress, Aix-La-Chapelle.
Photographic Collections
Photographs taken during Porcher and Smith's 10 month excavation in Cyrene are housed in London and Edinburgh, and comprise the earliest photographic views of the Necropolis at Cyrene. The London Album (British Museum) consists of 42 photographs. The Edinburgh Album (National Library of Scotland) consists of 38 photographs, and contains duplicates of the London album. See History of the Recent Discoveries at Cyrene made during an Expedition to the Cyrenaica in 1860-1 (London 1864), for published versions of these photographs.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series: I. Drawings; II. Diary and logbooks; III. Miscellaneous.
Titles for the drawings are transcribed from Porcher's contemporary inscriptions and include his original numbering scheme. The drawings are ordered numerically, within each subseries.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Primary Sources
Primary Sources
"Attack on Chinese Pirates by the Boats of Her Majesty's Ship 'Cleopatra'" The Illustrated London News, October 4, 1851. No. 520, Vol. 19. 401-402.
Baird, Charles W. History of the Huguenot Emigration to America. Vol. 2. New York: Dodd, Mead, 1885.
The British Colonist. July 31, 1867; August 2, 1867. Edwin Porcher file [excerpts], British Columbia Archives.
Davis, Nathan. Carthage and Her Remains: Being an Account of the Excavations and Researches on the Site of the Phœnician Metropolis in Africa, and Other Adjacent Places. London: R. Bentley, 1861.
"Discoveries at Cyrene," The Saturday review of Politics, Literature, Science and Art, 19:483 (1865: Jan. 28), p. 120.
Eighth Annual Report of the Columbia Mission for the Year 1866. London: Rivingtons, 1867.
Eleventh Annual Report of the Columbia Mission for the Year 1869. London: Rivingtons, 1870.
England & Wales, FreeBMD Marriage Index, 1837-1915. record for Edwin Augustus Porcher, [Ancestry.com]
England and Wales, National Probate Calendar (Index of Wills and Administrations), 1858-1966 record for Edwin Augustus Porcher, [Ancestry.com]
"Fresh Antiquities from Cyrene for the British Museum," Examiner (London: 1808), 2805 (1861:Nov. 2) p.701
Jukes, J. Beete, R. G. Latham, F. J. Evans, Richard Owen, John Edward Gray, Adam White, Harden Sidney Melville, John Dower, and George Norman. Narrative of the Surveying Voyage of H.M.S. Fly: Commanded by Captain F. P. Blackwood, R.N., in Torres Strait, New Guinea, and Other Islands of the Eastern Archipelago, during the Years 1842-1846: Together with an Excursion into the Interior of the Eastern Part of Java. London: T. & W. Boone, 1847.
London Gazette. October 20, 1868, 5510.
Melville, H.S. Sketches in Australia and the adjacent islands: selected from a number taken during the surveying voyage of H.M.S. "Fly" and "Bramble" under the command of Capt. F. P Blackwood […] 1842-46. London: Dickinson & Co., 1849.
The Nautical Standard and Steam Navigation Gazette. August 22, 1846. London: Office of the Nautical Standard, 1847-1854.
"New Cyrenaic Sculptures," London Review and Weekly Journal of Politics, Literature, Art and Society. 3:54 (1861: July 13) p. 43.
Ninth Annual Report of the Columbia Mission for the Year 1867. London: Rivingtons, 1868.
"Piracy in the China Seas," The Nautical Magazine and Naval Chronicle for 1852. New York: Cambridge UP, 2013.222.
"Promotions and Appointments," The Nautical Standard. 22 Aug 1846. 532.
Smith, R. Murdoch, and Edwin Augustus Porcher. History of the Recent Discoveries at Cyrene: Made during an Expedition to the Cyrenaica in 1860-61, under the Auspices of Her Majesty's Government. London: Day, 1864
"Societies," Athenaeum (1863:Jan. 17) p.89 [Porcher's election to Royal Geographic Society]
Tenth Annual Report of the Columbia Mission for the Year 1868. London: Rivingtons, 1869.
Veer, Gerrit De. The Three Voyages of William Barents to the Arctic Regions (1594, 1595, and 1596). London: Hakluyt Society., 1876. [Porcher's membership in the Hakluyt Society]
Secondary / Historical Background
Secondary / Historical Background
Abinales, P. N., and Donna J. Amoroso. State and Society in the Philippines. Lanham, MD: Rowman & Littlefield, 2005.
Atauz, Ayse Devrim. Eight Thousand Years of Maltese Maritime History: Trade, Piracy, and Naval Warfare in the Central Mediterranean. Gainesville: U of Florida, 2008.
Badger, George Percy. Description of Malta and Gozo. Malta: M. Weiss, 1838.
Barker, Ernest. Traditions of Civility; Eight Essays. Cambridge: U, 1948.
Cassar, Carmel. A Concise History of Malta. Msida, Malta: Mireva, 2000.
Dickinson, Harry W. Educating the Royal Navy: Eighteenth- and Nineteenth-century Education for Officers. London: Routledge, 2007.
Freed, Joann. Bringing Carthage Home: The Excavations of Nathan Davis, 1856-1859. Oxford, UK: Oxbow, for the Department of Classical, Near Eastern and Religious Studies, U of British Columbia, 2011.
Gatewood, James Duncan. Notes on Naval Hospitals, Medical Schools, and Training School for Nurses, with a Sketch of Hospital History. Baltimore: Press of the Friedenwald, 1893.
Ingham, Mike. Hong Kong: A Cultural History. Oxford: Oxford UP, 2007.
Jackson, Ashley. Buildings of Empire. Oxford: Oxford Univ., 2013.
Lambert, Andrew D. The Crimean War: British Grand Strategy, 1853-56. Manchester: Manchester UP, 1990.
Martin, R. Montgomery. History of the British Colonial Possessions in the Mediterranean. London: Henry G. Bohn, 1837.
"Melville, Harden Sydney." Design and Art Australia Online. 1992.Online. http://www.daao.org.au/bio/harden-sidney-melville/biography/
Moyal, A. (1986), A Bright and Savage land, Scientists in Colonial Australia. Sydney: Collins, 1986.
Munn, Christopher. Anglo-China: Chinese People and British Rule in Hong Kong. 1841-1880. Richmond: Curzon, 2001.
Nesbitt, J.K. "Captain Porcher Studied Indians and Coral," Victoria Daily Colonist. Islander (supplement). September 3, 1967, 2.
Nield, Robert. The China Coast: Trade and the First Treaty Ports. Hong Kong: Joint Pub., 2010.
O'Byrne, William R. A Naval Biographical Dictionary Compromising the Life and Services of Every Living Officer in Her Majesty's Navy, from the Rank of Admiral of the Fleet to That of Lieutenant, Inclusive. London: J. Murray, 1849.
Perdue, Peter C. "Rise and Fall of the Canton Trade System," MIT Visualizing Cultures. Online. http://ocw.mit.edu/ans7870/21f/21f.027/rise_fall_canton_02/index.html
Phillips, Simon and Emmanuel Buttigieg. Islands and Military Orders. Farnham: Ashgate Group, 2013.
Pieris, Anoma. Hidden Hands and Divided Landscapes: A Penal History of Singapore's Plural Society. Honolulu: U of Hawaii, 2009.
"Porcher, Edwin Augustus," Design and Art Australia Online. Online.http://www.daao.org.au/bio/edwin-augustus-porcher/
Porcher, Edwin Augustus, and Dwight La Vern Smith. A Tour of Duty in the Pacific Northwest: E.A. Porcher and H.M.S. Sparrowhawk, 1865-1868. Fairbanks, AK: U of Alaska, 2000.
Rowland, M.J. The Whitsunday Islands: Initial Historical and Archaeological Observations and Implications for Future Work. Archaeology Branch, Dept of community Services, Brisbane, University of Queensland, 1986. [reproduction of Porcher's "Outrigger canoe at Cape Hillsborough, page 75].
Savours, A. & McConnell, A. "The history of the Rossbank Observatory, Tasmania," Annals of Science. Vol. 39. [London]: Taylor & Francis, c1982.
Searle, Ross. Artist in the Tropics: 200 Years of Art in North Queensland. Townsville, Qld.: Perc Tucker Regional Gallery, 1991. 13, 16.
Sorlini, Giulia B. ""The Megalithic Temples of Malta"" Archaeology and Fertility Cult in the Ancient Mediterranean: Papers Presented at the First International Conference on Archaeology of the Ancient Mediterranean. The University of Malta, 2-5 September 1985. Ed. Anthony Bonanno. Amsterdam: B.R. Grüner Pub., 1986
Thorn, Dorothy M. The Four Seasons of Cyrene: The Excavation and Explorations in 1861 of Lieutenants R. Murdoch Smith, R.E. and Edwin A. Porcher. R.N. Roma: L'Erma Di Bretschneider, 2007.
Toksöz, Meltem, and Cayla Keyvanian. "Maps and Wars: Charting the Mediterranean in the Sixteenth Century" Cities of the Mediterranean: From the Ottomans to the Present Day. By Biray Kolluoğlu. London: I.B. Tauris, 2010.
Whitworth, George Clifford. An Anglo-Indian Dictionary: A Glossary of Indian Terms Used in English, and of Such English or Other Non-Indian Terms as Have Obtained Special Meanings in India. London: K. Paul, Trench, 1885.
Wong, Hong Suen, and Roxana Waterson. Singapore through 19th Century Prints & Paintings. Singapore: National Museum of Singapore, 2010.
Wright, G.R.H. "By Seaways to Cyrene: Captain E.A. Porcher R.N., water colorist, before Smith and Porcher," BAR international series. Oxford: British Archaeological Reports, 2006.
Anglo-Burmese War, 2nd, 1852; Antiquities; Excavations (Archaeology); Fortification; Harbors -- China -- Pictorial works; Junks -- Pictorial works; Navigation; Pagodas -- Burma -- Pictorial works; Piracy -- China; Pirates -- China; Punic antiquities; Ships -- Pictorial works; Temples -- China -- Pictorial works; Voyages and travels -- 1850-1900; Carthage (Extinct city) -- Pictorial works; China Sea -- Description and travel; Cyrene (Extinct city) -- Pictorial works; East Asia -- Description and travel; Gozo Island (Malta) -- Pictorial works; Grand Harbour (Malta) -- Pictorial works; Great Britain -- Colonies -- Asia; Guangzhou (China) -- Description and travel; Hong Kong (China) -- Pictorial works; Hong Kong (China) -- Description and travel; Malta -- Pictorial works; Malta -- Antiquities; Malta -- Description and travel; Malta -- History, Naval; Mellieh̳a (Malta) -- Pictorial works; Pulau Pinang (Malaysia: State) -- Pictorial works; Qrendi (Malta) -- Pictorial works; Singapore -- Pictorial works; Trincomalee (Sri Lanka) -- Pictorial works; Tunis (Tunisia) -- Pictorial works; Tunisia -- Antiquities, Roman -- Pictorial works; Utica (Extinct city) -- Pictorial works; Valletta (Malta) -- Pictorial works; Diaries; Letters; Ships' logs; Watercolors (paintings); Chron -- 1849-1861; Davis, N. (Nathan), 1812-1882; Melville, Harden Sidney, active 1837-1882; Porcher, Edwin A., 1824-1878; Porcher, Madelina -- Correspondence; Great Britain. Royal Navy -- Officers; Great Britain. Royal Navy; Boxer (Ship: 1855-1865); Cleopatra (Ship: 1843); Harpy (Ship: 1845-1909); Hibernia (Ship: 1804-1902); Kertch (Ship)
- Drawings, Series I
  - Drawings from the HMS Cleopatra
    - 1. India. The Caves of Elephanta near Bombay. March 1850., 1850 March; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, heightened with white, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 25.5 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Depicts naval officers drinking and dining in the Elephanta Caves, near present-day Mumbai. Porcher may have looked to models such as 'The Temple of Elephanta': line engraving by James Phillips after painting by James Wales, based on an original drawing by James Forbes (Published London, 1790). Porcher's signature appears on the bottom left corner.
      General
      B1977. 14.22203
      Elephanta Island (India); Cave temples -- India; Watercolors; Great Britain. Royal Navy
    - 2. Ceylon. Bungalow at Sober Island Trincomalie. Sept. 1850., 1850 September; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, heightened with white, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 20 x 29 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      B1977.14.22204
      Watercolors; Trincomalee (Sri Lanka)
    - 3. Ceylon. Bathing place at Sober Island. Trincomalie. September 1850., 1850 September; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, heightened with white, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 20 x 29 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      B1977.14.22205
    - 4. Burmah. Pagodas Rangoon. April 7th 1853., 1853 April 7; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, heightened with white, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 19.5 x 28.5 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      Porcher describes the pagodas of Rangoon in his journal: "The town of Rangoon is situated on the north shore of a considerable branch of the river that extends to the westward about a league, and is about 24 miles from the entrance. The Dagon Pagoda supposed to be the finest in this part of the country, and held in high veneration by the natives by its containing light true hairs of Gautama, is about 2 miles from the town in a NNW direction, on an elevation of 487 feet above high water level, part of which is supposed to be artificial. It commands a fine view of the surrounding country, and both branches of the river" (65). Porcher has pictured himself sitting, sketching the scene depicted. George Hunt's illustrations for Rangoon Views (1825-26) may have been an artistic model for Porcher's view.
      B1977.14.22206
      Pagodas -- Burma; Watercolors; Rangoon (Burma); Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878
    - 5. Burmah. Pagodas at Mopoon near Moulmein. April 18th 1853., 1853 April 18; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, heightened with white, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 26 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      B1977.14.22207
      Pagodas -- Burma; Moulmein (Burma); Watercolors
    - 6. Burmah. Principal pagodas at Moulmein, Martaban and the Salween river in the distance. April 28th 1853., 1853 April 28; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, heightened with white, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 25 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      Porcher describes the significance of the significance of the Martaban river as "the boundary between the Burmese dominions, and the territory ceded to the British Government" (66). The date of the watercolor roughly corresponds to a letter sent to his sister, Madelina, in which he briefly describes conditions following the Second Anglo-Burmese war (see Miscellaneous series, 1853 letter).
      B1977.14.22208
      Pagodas -- Burma; Salween River; Martaban, Gulf of (Burma); Moulmein (Burma); Watercolors
    - 7. China. Hong Kong from the Capsingmoon Passage. July 30, 1852., 1852 July 30; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, heightened with white, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 26 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      "HONG KONG" is inscribed in the lower left corner.
      B1977.14.22209
      Hong Kong (China); Watercolors
    - 8. Hong Kong from Lyemoon Passage. September 8, 1852., 1852 September 1852; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, heightened with white, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 25.5. x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      Visible in the distance is Victoria Peak, which dominated early views of the city. Settlement soon began to encroach higher as the city expanded, with the most prestigious Western-style settlements on the peak.
      B1977.14.22210
    - 9. Hong Kong from the opposite main land. October 6, 1852., 1852 October 6; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, heightened with white, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 25.5 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      B1977.14.22211
      Hong Kong (China); Junks; Watercolors
    - 10. Hong Kong from the beach road, leading to the Happy Valley. December 9, 1852., 1852 December 9; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 26 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      This representation illustrates the fashion of British colonial modes of transport by the early 1850s. Chinese figures carry a palanquin, while a horse-drawn carriage also charges by. Happy Valley was the site of a British racecourse and a Protestant Cemetery (see watercolor "11").
      B1977.14.22212
      Hong Kong (China); Happy Valley (Hong Kong, China); Watercolors
    - 11. Hong Kong. Protestant cemetery in the Happy Valley. October 26, 1852., 1852 October 26; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, heightened with white, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 24.5 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      The Hong Kong Cemetery (also known as the Protestant Cemetery and the Colonial Cemetery) was opposite the oldest racecourse in Hong Kong in Happy Valley, and in the middle of a line of cemeteries that included the Roman Catholic cemetery (founded 1848) and later Islamic cemetery (1870). In 1853 (a year after this view), the captain and crew of the HMS Cleopatra erected a monument to Scottish trader and explorer Robert Burns, grandson of the poet, who was killed by pirates of the Tunku River (for which the Cleopatra was dispatched to avenge, see watercolors '25' and '27').
      B1977.14.22213
    - 12. Hong Kong. Chinese man of war junk mounting 27 Guns. Mandarin's Flag (Blue button at the Fore). July 26, 1851., 1851 July 26; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, heightened with white, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 25.2 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      Since the Song Dynasty, ocean-going junks of this size made trips to Southeast Asia and the Indian Ocean.
      B1977.14.22214
      Junks; Watercolors; Hong Kong (China)
    - 13. Hong Kong. Canton trading junks at anchor in the harbour. July 1851., 1851 July; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, heightened with white, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 24 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      B1977.14.22215
      Watercolors; Hong Kong (China); Junks
    - 14. Hong Kong. HMS Cleopatra lying off Jardine's establishment. November 22, 1852., 1852 November 22; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, heightened with white, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 26 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      B1977.14.22216